<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable Sir Henry Tulse, Lord Mayor of the city of London and the court of aldermen, together with the governors of the hospitals at the parish-church of St. Bridget, on Easter Monday, March 31, 1684 by the Right Reverend Father in God Francis Lord Bishop of Rochester ...</title>
            <author>Turner, Francis, 1638?-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63883</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3284</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38919</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18189597</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18189597</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106986</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63883)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106986)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1133:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable Sir Henry Tulse, Lord Mayor of the city of London and the court of aldermen, together with the governors of the hospitals at the parish-church of St. Bridget, on Easter Monday, March 31, 1684 by the Right Reverend Father in God Francis Lord Bishop of Rochester ...</title>
                  <author>Turner, Francis, 1638?-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], iii, [1], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Benj. Tooke...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke XIV, 13-14 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:106986:1"/>
            <opener>
               <signed>Tulſe Mayor.</signed>
               <dateline>Curia ſpecial. tent. <date>die Mercurii in Hebdomad. Feſt. Paſch. ſecund. April. 1684. Anno<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Reg. Regis Caroli Secundi Angliae, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> xxxvi.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>THIS Court doth deſire the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>Francis</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi> to Print his Sermon, Preached in St. <hi>Bridgets</hi> Church on <hi>Monday</hi> laſt, before the Lord Mayor and Aldermen of this City.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Wagſtaffe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106986:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd before the Right Honourable Sir Henry Tulſe, LORD MAYOR OF <hi>The City of London:</hi> And the COURT of ALDERMEN, Together with the Governors of the Hoſpitals.</p>
            <p>AT The Pariſh-Church of St. <hi>Bridget,</hi> on <hi>Eaſter</hi> Monday, <hi>March</hi> 31. 1684.</p>
            <p>By the Right Reverend Father in God <hi>FRANCIS</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> and Almoner to His Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>j. <hi>Tooke,</hi> at the Ship in Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:106986:2"/>
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:106986:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable Sir Henry Tulſe, LORD MAYOR OF THE CITY OF LONDON: And to the Honourable Court of ALDERMEN.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS I ſhow'd the juſt Deference I had and muſt ever have to your Lordſhip, and to all the worthy Governours of this great City, when upon the firſt Intimation of the Choice you had done me the favour to make of me, I was ready to ſerve your Devotions, ſo upon the ſignification of your pleaſure, that I ſhould publiſh this Diſcourſe, tho' fitter for a Popular
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:106986:3"/> Audience, than for the Preſs, it would ill ſuit with the Office I have the Honouor to bear of Diſtributing the Royal Alms, ſhould I any longer delay ſo ſlender a Contribution as This to the City-Charity, to be one of your Remembrancers, and Solicitors in that behalf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lord,</hi> While I Exhort you to do what is not only your Duty but your Practice, I take the only courſe that is proper for One in my Station to Adorn you and yet not Flater you, nay to Commend you without any Complement; eſpecially for your perpetual and moſt Loyal Care of the Publick Peace, which does ſo migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily befriend all Publick Works of Charity, you that preſerve it by duly <hi>Exerciſing your Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> tho' you are far from Affecting the <hi>ſtyle of Benefactors,</hi> yet you are ſuch and more, in ſubordination to His Majeſty; who as from His Firſt Wonderful <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Happy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration He may juſtly Wear That Glorious Title, <hi>The Repairer of the Breach.</hi> So upon the Late no leſs happy, and perhaps all things conſider'd, no leſs wonderful Re-Eſtabliſhment of the Government, and Re-Settlement of ſo many
<pb n="iii" facs="tcp:106986:3"/> Diſorder'd Corporations, He may be truly ſtyled, <hi>The Reſtor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r of Citys to dwell in:</hi> For a Great City grows an Inhoſpitable if not an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitable Place, and may be properly called a Great Wilderneſs, when the Bonds of Civil Government, which is ſo abſolutely Neceſſary to keep Humane Society together, are broken aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: Your Names will be famous in our <hi>Story,</hi> who under God and the King, have been ſo In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental in bringing back Excellent Order where Confuſion, or which is all one, the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude began to Reign: That it may pleaſe God to Proſper and Perfect all Your Honourable and Charitable <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakings is my Hearty Prayer.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>I am Your Lordſhip's moſt Obedient and moſt Humble Servant, Fran. Roffens.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:106986:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106986:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED On St. <hi>Luke</hi> xiv. 13, 14.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But when thou makeſt a Feaſt, call the Poor, the Maimed, the Lame, the Blind:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And thou ſhalt be Bleſſed; for they cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſe thee: for thou ſhalt be recompenſed at the Reſurrection of the Juſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WELL and Wiſely has the Piety of thoſe that went before us, (a Piety worthily follow'd by the preſent Noble Senators of this Great City) Ordain'd and Appointed, that theſe Holy Feſtival-Days, which wait upon Eaſter-Day, ſhould be Honour'd with theſe ſolemn Aſſemblies, and that in order to theſe two Great and Good Ends; in the firſt place, That of Praiſing God with the reſt of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106986:5"/> Chriſtian World, for the Glorious Reſurrection of our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour; in the ſecond place, That of ſtirring up our Affections to ſuch Good Works and Alms Deeds, as ſhall not fail to obtain their Ample <hi>Recompence</hi> at <hi>the Reſurrection of the Juſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now both theſe weighty ſubjects, the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Charity, which ſhall then receive its Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Rewards, are joyn'd in my Text, and it will challenge your beſt and moſt awful Attention, if you will but conſider how Chriſt has put them together in another Text; where he gives us the ſame comfortable Expectation as he does here; but alſo a terrible warning that the particular Teſt and Tryal of all men at the General Reſurrection ſhall be, their having perform'd or neglected theſe Offices of Charity to the Poor, the Hungry, the Naked, or any way diſtreſſed Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>To find out and ſhew you the full extent and deſign of our Saviour's words in the Text, 'tis neceſſary to look back and lay before you the Occaſion upon which they were ſpoken; Our Lord you know was ſo Charitable, ſo Condeſcending as to make himſelf Familiar, and in a manner Domeſtique to thoſe that were none of the beſt, becauſe he was ſtill in hopes of doing them ſome good; and having been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected upon by the Phariſees for <hi>Eating with Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans,</hi> now to prevent their Murmuring he ſuffers himſelf to be over-entreated and invited by <hi>one of the Chief of the Phariſees to Eat Bread in his Houſe;</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:106986:5"/> where it quickly appear'd they had at leaſt as much need of his Advice to Cure the Diſtempers of their minds, as had thoſe whom they contemptuouſly ſtiled <hi>Sinners;</hi> for preſently 'tis ſed, that againſt all the Laws of Hoſpitality, <hi>they watcht Him,</hi> that was, to ſteal His Words, or to find ſomewhat in his Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to Accuſe and Defame him; the Bait they had laid as moſt likely to take him, was a Work of Charity, <hi>A Man to be healed of a Dropſy;</hi> But it was their Saboath-Day, and when he puts them the Caſe of Conſcience, Whether it were Lawful to heal him then or no, <hi>they held their Peace,</hi> but with intent to make noiſe enough of it afterward, in caſe he proceeded to work the Miracle of Mercy, which nevertheleſs he did with a generous undaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted freedom, and then what he had done he main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd with that ſtrength of Argument, as he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced them to an abſolute Incapacity <hi>of Anſwering him again to theſe things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now though they had utterly ſpoyl'd the Grace of the Treat they had given him, by <hi>making his Table a Snare to him,</hi> yet he <hi>whoſe Meat it was to do the Will of him that ſent him, and to finiſh his Work;</hi> reſolves to make a Spiritual Entertainment for them, who had pretended to oblige him, by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viting him to partake with them their Corporal Food; and firſt he gives them to underſtand, That he would not Abridge their juſt Liberties of Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining, nor even of Feaſting one another; but he would Regulate theſe Civil Meetings of theirs, <hi>when
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106986:6"/> he markt how they choſe out the Chief Rooms;</hi> he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects them how they may turn ſuch Commerces and Correſpondences as are neceſſary to ſupport the Dignity and Comfort of Human Society, into the Exerciſes of Virtue, of that fundamental Virtue profound Humility, if they will change their Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice which ſavour'd too much of Pride, and if they will take his Counſel, <hi>To go and ſit down in the loweſt Room.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And having Preach'd to them Humility at their Publick Feaſts, then he goes on to Teach and ſhew them <hi>a more Excellent way,</hi> as the Apoſtle calls it, that is <hi>Charity;</hi> Addreſſing himſelf to him that bade him to Dinner, and with him probably many other Gueſts, <hi>Friends, Brethren,</hi> or <hi>Kinſmen,</hi> or <hi>rich Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,</hi> with an eye to ſome mean Advantage or pitiful Intereſt, that they ſhould make him a ſuitable Return either in the ſame kind, or in equal value; he does not forbid this mutual kindneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Relations, as if it were a Crime in it ſelf, but he puts him in mind, that all this may be no Virtue, that this may be nothing to Charity, nor yet advance one ſtep in the way to Heaven. But if in ſted of the <hi>Rich</hi> he would <hi>Call the Poor,</hi> in ſted of his <hi>Kindred</hi> the Stranger that is in Want, in ſted of his <hi>Friends and Neighbours</hi> that do not need a Meals-meat from him, and can afford him as good Cheer again, he would make much of thoſe that can do nothing to help themſelves, <hi>The Maimed, the Lame, the Blind,</hi> ſuch as cannot Retribute any
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106986:6"/> thing to him their Entertainer and Benefactor: then would the Hoſpitality be of the Nobleſt Kind, it would be perfect Charity, and he ſhould <hi>be Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed at the Reſurrection of the Juſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words then are eaſily divided into theſe four Parts:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Here is a general expreſs Precept for Alms-Deeds, A <hi>Charge to them that are Rich in this World, that they be ready to give, and apt to diſtribute, Call the Poor:</hi> 'Tis ſpoken to the Maſter of the Houſe, and in him to all others of the like Ability.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Here is matter of Precept mixt and joyn'd with matter of Counſel and Advice, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Manner, the Meaſures, the Rules of Proportion and Decency to be obſerv'd in doing our Alms-Deeds: Here are excellent Directions given us to do them preſently, and with our own Hands rather than leave them to be done by others after our Deaths, to do them Diligently, Chearfully, Plentifully, nay <hi>Openly</hi> ſometimes, as well as <hi>Secretly</hi> at other times; to do them with all the Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending Kindneſs of Entertainers, for ſuch good natur'd qualifications as theſe are implied in theſe words, <hi>When thou makeſt a Feaſt, Call the Poor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Choice of fit Objects for the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Rich is here determin'd, they muſt be ſuch as are Poor indeed, for ſuch they are not, nor are they properly ſo call'd that are in condition to help themſelves, they muſt be really helpleſs Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>the Maimed, the Lame, the Blind.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106986:7"/> Fourthly and Laſtly,</hi> Here is ſet before us the moſt forcible Inducement, the ſtrongeſt Motive to Charity, the great Reward of it, and the greater by far the later it is Repay'd; the Danger is only leaſt a <hi>Recompenſe be made thee</hi> too ſoon; but if thou canſt be Contented to ſtay a while, here is offer'd the ſirmeſt Security, that thou <hi>ſhalt be Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed at the Reſurrection of the Juſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt here is a general expreſs Precept for Alms-Deeds, A <hi>Charge to them that are Rich in this World that they be ready to give, and apt to diſtribute, Call the Poor:</hi> 'Tis ſpoken to the Maſter of the Houſe, and in him to all others of the like Ability.</p>
            <p>For as Chriſt made this Exhortation to one of their Chiefs, ſo by parity of Reaſon it extends it ſelf to thoſe, and to thoſe eſpecially <hi>that bear Rule, Men Renowned for their Power, Leaders of the People by their Counſel, Rich Men furniſht with Ability, living peaceably in their Habitations;</hi> Theſe are the Titles of Honour which the Book of Wiſdome beſtows upon you, and to ſuch as you is this word of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand given by the Lord of Life, that ye conſider the Poor; for to this the Providence of God in the Beautiful Ordering of the World, and Ranging Mankind into ſeveral Degrees and Ranks, has giv'n you a ſpecial Call, to look down from your High but Slippery Places, with an Eye of Pity upon thoſe that lye at your Feet and can fall no lower; ſuch is the wonderful and uſeful variety of Gods Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations to Men, that ſome <hi>even hired Servants in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106986:7"/> our Father's houſe have enough and to ſpare,</hi> while many a <hi>Son</hi> (and he not always a <hi>Prodigal)</hi> is <hi>ready to periſh with Hunger;</hi> and though King <hi>David</hi> after very long Experience was able to ſay, <hi>I have been Young and now am Old, and yet ſaw I never the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous forſaken, nor his Seed begging their Bread,</hi> that is, not Abandoned to a ſtate of Beggery or craving of Alms without finding Relief, ſuch a heavy Curſe as that was denounced by <hi>David</hi> only againſt the Children of the Traytor <hi>Judas, to be Vagabonds and begg their Bread, to ſeek it alſo out of Deſolate Places;</hi> yet that there ſhould be ſome in a mean and low Condition, is as neceſſary as that others ſhould Abound; for an equality of Wealth and Honour would be impoſſible, and a Levelling Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple can never be reduc'd to practice: For if all Men were Princes whom ſhould each Govern? if none were Poor, who ſhou'd do ſervile Offices, and who ſhou'd then ſupply the Neceſſities of the Rich? I am apt to think that the greateſt Alteration that ever happen'd in theſe Weſtern Parts of the World, except when Chriſtianity came in, was, when That by degrees turn'd out Slavery, the <hi>Roman</hi> Abſolute Slavery, under which an incredible number of Men were ſubject to their Maſters as to ſo many Monarchs that had Power of Life and Death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> over them; but what a Change would it be, if not only Slavery were gone out of the World, but Service alſo and Dependance of Inferiors upon thoſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106986:8"/> that are Exalted with Honour, of the Needy upon thoſe that live at Eaſe and in Plenty; All thoſe who know not now what it is to want, the Scene being ſo chang'd, would ſtand more in need of help than any do now of relief; Conſider it then as a Bounty of God to the Rich, that <hi>the Poor ſhall never ceaſe out of the Land,</hi> 'tis a Promiſe, a Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Promiſe, <hi>Deut.</hi> xv. 11. And Bleſs Almighty God for providing you theſe, not only <hi>as hewers of wood, and drawers of water,</hi> not only as helpers and ſupporters of your Temporal State, for the daily preſſing neceſſities of Human Life, but as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provers of all your Spiritual Graces, Objects of your Comiſeration, ſuch as may call inceſſantly upon every tender Paſſion within you, ſuch as may ſtir up Reſentments of Gratitude to that Good and Gracious Maſter, who might with perfect Juſtice have laid you as low as others whom you ſee in the Duſt; ſuch as may excite you to produce con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Acts of Love to that Bleſſed Saviour, who ſhed his moſt precious Blood, the Blood of God, for the very leaſt of theſe; and has prepar'd a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle in ſome of the many Manſions in his Father's Houſe, for many a wretch who during his Pilgrimage here, takes up that Lamentation, <hi>I have no place to flee in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o, and no man careth for my Soul;</hi> yet 'tis moſt dear unto God, and <hi>precious in the ſight of the Lord, is the death of any Saint;</hi> tho' he be as contemptible as <hi>Lazarus</hi> was in the Eye of the <hi>Rich Man,</hi> yet the Angels of God are to carry his better
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106986:8"/> part into the place of Reſt, if he be <hi>Rich in Faith,</hi> if he well perform that Part which God has Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed him in this Life; for as Human Life is aptly enough compar'd to the Acting upon a Stage, ſo he that Acts the Beggar well, and throughout maintains the decorum of the Perſon whom he ſuſtains, deſerves to be ſent off with as great Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, as he that ſtands for the Great Man in the Fable, ſince he is only the Richer Pageant of the two, and if it be truly ſaid by the Pſalmiſt that <hi>every Man is a Lye,</hi> then it may not be altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly ſaid, <hi>the Greater Man the Greater Lye.</hi> But if on the other ſide you ſee yet a ſadder Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle, that is pinching extream Poverty with lewd manners, for alaſs deſperate wickedneſs, and cruel want, are often found to joyn their hands, how uſeful is even ſuch an Object of Sin and Miſery together, in thoſe whom the Pſalmiſt deſcribes, <hi>that will run here and there for Meat, and grudge if they be not ſatisfied,</hi> 'tis well if they do not Curſe too, how inſtructive are ſuch miſerable ſights to make us pray heartily with the Son of <hi>Syrach, Give me neither Poverty nor Riches, feed me with food con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for me;</hi> not Riches, fore-ſeeing an evident Danger of Luxury and Epicuriſm leading to direct Atheiſm, <hi>leſt I be full and deny thee, and ſay who is the Lord?</hi> and Danger too on the other ſide, <hi>leſt I be Poor and ſteal, and take the Name of my God in vain;</hi> either forſwearing himſelf to get off from Puniſhment, facing Almighty God when he ſneaks
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106986:9"/> and ſhrinks from Man, or elſe 'tis meant of habitual common Swearing, which heretofore few would be guilty of (ſo Abject a Vice it was thought) but the meaneſt People of as little Honour as Conſcience.</p>
            <p>But beſides ſuch Reflections as theſe, which the ſight of the miſerable will ſuggeſt to raiſe and keep up Piety, 'tis our Advantage on another and greater Account, <hi>that the Poor we have always with us.</hi> Our Saviour has ſaid it as it were Congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating us the never-failing Opportunities of Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing our Charity; for were it not in Charity to us as well as to them, that we may do our ſelves good, has God any need of our Aid to provide for thoſe whoſe Condition ſeems ſo neceſſitous? <hi>Thou Lord of thy Goodneſs haſt prepared for the Poor,</hi> ſays the Royal Prophet, 'tis his Goodneſs to thoſe that give and not only to them that receive, that he will convey his Largeſſes through our hands to theirs, <hi>for all the Beaſts of the Forreſt are his,</hi> and <hi>ſo are the Cattel upon a thouſand Hills: If I be hungry,</hi> (ſays he the Great Creator, and ſo if the leaſt of his Creatures be hungry) <hi>I will not tell thee, for the whole World is mine, and all that is therein:</hi> Is there not Silver and Gold enough in the bowels of the Earth, and Pearls in the bottom of the Sea enow to ſatisfie all Mens wants, and leave none to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain in our Streets: or is God's Hand ſhorten'd that he cannot rain Quails again with Manna every Morning? ſo all Men <hi>ſhou'd Eat Angels Food, and have Meat enough;</hi> but the Divine Wiſdome is not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106986:9"/> wont to be laviſh of Miracles, and 'tis perfect Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to make us Men, God's Inſtruments, good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels as it were to Guard and Aſſiſt our fellows in their Extremity; nor is this left to our Choice to do it, or not to do it. I call'd it a Precept or a Command to the Rich, and it was the very form of Asking an Alms by the Poor among the <hi>Jews, Give me as God has appointed or bidden you to do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis an affirmative Precept, <hi>Call the Poor,</hi> and being ſuch does not oblige <hi>ad Semper,</hi> as the Schools uſe to ſpeak, that is, it does not bind us to do it at all times or without any Intermiſſion, whereas Negative Precepts as, <hi>Thou ſhalt do no Murther,</hi> does ſo perpetually oblige, that we may at no time break them; but perhaps there are few more dangerous fallacies, yet none more common than this, becauſe I cannot Charge another for wanting Charity, tho he be not opening of his Hand, and giving every minute of his Life, the Man, but 'tis the Old Man ſtill within us, will be apt to Conclude, if the duty of doing his Alms takes no faſt hold of him now, nor to morrow, nor at any ſet time hereafter, then when does it lye upon him? on this ſuppoſition i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will be very rarely or never Practis'd: It gives little leſs than a general Diſpenſation, tho not by Abſolving a Man from any Tye upon him, yet by repreſenting it as no moral ſin to defer it as lon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, as he pleaſes; yet all this while his Conſcience may quiet it ſelf: This was the Caſe of the Rich Young Man in the Goſpel, <hi>All the Commandments,</hi> ſaith he,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106986:10"/> 
               <hi>have I kept from my Youth.</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> and moſt others are of Opinion that he was no Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, yet we are ſure that he was not ſincerely a Saint; but he did not lay his uncharitable Omiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to Heart, for he that lov'd his Mony better than Chriſt, muſt needs have been guilty of <hi>ſhutting up his Bowels of Compaſſion</hi> many a time, <hi>when he ſaw his Brother have need,</hi> tho' his own memory could not perhaps reproach him with any one Odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Inſtance of having deny'd an Alms, when he thought himſelf ſtrictly bound in Conſcience to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow it. But now to ſtate our own Obligation.</p>
            <p>Firſt you may ſet it down as a certain Truth, that our Saviour here calls upon us to get the Habit of Charity, for the Habit of Uncharitableneſs is utterly inconſiſtent with a ſtate of Grace: Now a Habit of this nature cannot be gotten but by many Acts; and to think that one or a few inconſiderable Acts in the courſe of a Man's Life, will ſuffice to acquire and confirm this excellent Grace of Charity, 'tis as wild Divinity as that in the <hi>Jeſuits Morals,</hi> where they have the hardineſs to maintain, That one ſuch Act of Love to God, tho' no more be exerted by one Man, may ſerve his turn and Save him: Once then for all, we may take the perfect notion of this or any other Acquir'd Habit, from the great Philoſopher, who if he were not more a Divine, yet was leſs a Heathen is then many of thoſe <hi>Romiſh Caſuiſts.</hi> A Habit is then atrain'd when we have gain'd the Point upon our ſelves, to work as we
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106986:10"/> ought, with li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tle or no difficulty; If then we give not eaſily, willingly, conſtantly, or at leaſt very frequently, we are ſtill to learn and to ſeek for the Habit of Charity.</p>
            <p>I muſt needs ſay in the ſecond place, That ſome extraordinary Object of Compaſſion may be ſo preſſing and lye ſo hard on the Conſcience of any Chriſtian, as to bear it down, and the feed of Grace the Vital Act in the Heart may be utterly deſtroy'd for the preſent, if he turns away his Face and does not put forth his hand to ſave his Brother, for whom Chriſt was pleaſed to Dye. The Prieſt and Levite who paſt by the Poor Man that had fallen among Thieves, and left him there weltring in his Blood, they drew it no doubt upon their own heads, and are Condemn'd by the Mouth of our Bleſſed Lord, for ſo not loving their Neighbour, as if they had been Acceſſories to the killing of him: nay Principals not only in mortally Wounding his Body, but their own Souls.</p>
            <p>But I muſt alſo offer this as my Third Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, That a Paſſionate, a Vehement, an Affectionate, or for want of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> word to hit my Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons fully, give me leave to call it an <hi>Affectuous</hi> ſetting the Heart upon Wealth and worldy Goods, more than upon Heaven and the way to Heaven by Charity, is a ſtate of Sin and of Death: tho the Conſcience like his who had great Poſſeſſions be ſo partial to its ſelf, as being not throughly Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, to make a Return <hi>not Guilty</hi> of any Groſs
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106986:11"/> Omiſſions in this kind, or of any notorious Act of Uncharitable dealing, or of any Habit to make one appear Hard-hearted, yet if your Treaſure be upon Earth and your Souls be ſet upon it, they muſt needs be ſtak'd down here too, and mount no higher; for it is a Judg'd Caſe, and with all the Reaſon in the world, That <hi>where your Treaſure is, there will your Hearts be alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be Objected and Thoughts may ariſe in your Hearts, if there be ſo much danger of doing too little and too ſlender Alms; then What is enough for the Rich to beſtow upon Charity? ſhall I ſay, whatever they can ſpare from their own Occaſions? that will not advance one foot toward ſtating the Queſtion; 'tis only raiſing another, a harder Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, which the beſt Caſuiſts will never be able to ſettle. <hi>De abjiciendo Superfluo,</hi> of the parting with our ſuperfluity to relieve thoſe in need or neceſſity. But what is ſuperabundance to ſome, is ſcarce a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency to others in different Circumſtances; Upon the whole matter, no preciſe bounds and limits can be ſet for all Men, nor for any two Men in the World, tho we could ſuppoſe them exactly alike in Minds, Bodies and Eſtates; It muſt be when all is done, in taking the meaſures of this or any other Chriſtian Graces, <hi>prout vir prudens definiverit,</hi> as Old Philoſophy could never otherwiſe aſſign the conſtant Exerciſe of moral Virtues its juſt Amplia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Reſtrictions, but only as Prudence ſhould define them in particular Caſes; indeed to ſuit this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106986:11"/> with Divinity it muſt be Chriſtian Prudence, that is well guided Piety or Conſcience wiſely directed; Nor do's the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> go very much farther towards fixing the definite Proportions of <hi>Charity</hi> in the almoſt infinite Circumſtances of men, than the Maſters of our morals had gone before him, in deſcribing the Lines and Limits of what they called <hi>Mercy;</hi> only St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſeems to enjoyn one thing neceſſary to Enter and Engage good Chriſtians in a Courſe of Charity, that they all ſhould have ſet times as they are the Stewards of God, to make up their Accounts for <hi>Pious <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes,</hi> that theſe ſet times ſhould be ſo near one another, as to keep the Trade of Charity quick, <hi>upon the firſt day of the week let every one of you lay by him in ſtore;</hi> But when it comes to naming the Sum that every one muſt allow, St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf could not offer any common meaſure, he does not decimate or call upon them for a <hi>Temh,</hi> nor yet for a <hi>Twentieth Part,</hi> or Exact upon them at any determinate Rate, <hi>But let every one lay by him in ſtore as God hath proſpered him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be Reply'd that this is to leave our Duty at ſuch Uncertainty, as makes it hard to know when our <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> that is, our <hi>Charity exceeds</hi> theirs who <hi>ſhall by no means enter into the Kingdom of Heaven:</hi> my Anſwer is, All ſuch Scruples are eaſily removed, if inſted of diſputing how much 'tis our Obligation to give, we fall to practiſing and <hi>aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the Work of the Lord,</hi> this is to take the ſafe and the high-way to Heaven. And this falls in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106986:12"/> with my ſecond Part: Here is a matter of Precept mixt and joyn'd with matter of Counſel and Advice concerning the Manner, the Meaſures, the Rules of Proportion and Decency to be obſerved in doing our Alms-Deeds, Here are excellent Directions given us to do them preſently, and with our own hands, rather than leave them to be done by others after our Deaths; to do them Diligently, Chearfully, Plentifully, nay Openly ſometimes as well as Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly at other times, to do them with all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcending Kindneſs of Entertainers, for ſuch good natur'd Qualifications as theſe are implyed in theſe words: <hi>When thou makeſt a Feaſt, Call the Poor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſaying differs much from that other ſaying; <hi>Sell what you have and give to the Poor,</hi> ſo ſays our Bleſſed Saviour, St. <hi>Luke</hi> xii. but it is a plain Caſe, That was only propos'd and advis'd to ſome, never impos'd by Chriſt upon any but one, that Rich Young Man we ſpoke of; His Caſe was ſingular; Our Lord diſcerned him to be as worldly as wealthy, therefore it was neceſſary for his <hi>Eternal Salvation,</hi> to part him and his Great Poſſeſſions; But good Amends would have been preſently made him, he would have been admitted to be one of the Peculiar Followers of Jeſus, and probably the Power of working Miracles would have been given him: But for the Generality of Mankind they are left free, and forced upon none of theſe Extraordinary Attainments, whether they will or no; He <hi>that lyed to the Holy-Ghoſt</hi> in the matter of Alms was told
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106986:12"/> by St. <hi>Peter, While the Land remained was it not thine own, and after it was ſold was it not in thine own power?</hi> that is to do what he pleas'd with the Money paid fot it. And yet <hi>ſuch as ſould their Lands, and laid the prices at the Apoſtles feet, and Diſtribution was made unto every man according as he had need,</hi> theſe have that Character immediately given them, that <hi>Great Grace was upon them all.</hi> Notwithſtanding which, to ſay that our Saviours words in St. <hi>Luke, Sell what you have and give to the Poor,</hi> obliges the Rich to part with all, or as <hi>Zacheus</hi> did, (and it was well done of him) with the <hi>one half of his Goods to the Poor,</hi> this was one dangerous part of <hi>Pelagius'es</hi> Hereſie. Therefore Chriſt did not pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſs that <hi>Publican</hi> to ſo vaſt a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of Alms as he gave unaskt, and then Chriſt Graciouſly Accepted it; nor does Chriſt Labour <hi>the Phariſee</hi> in my Text, to deveſt himſelf of his whole Eſtate at once; But implies ſufficiently that it was Lawful for him to keep up ſome port, and to abide in a Condition of ſometimes <hi>making a Feaſt;</hi> Nor can I think it unlawful for you that are Mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of uſeful Bounties, to keep up the Honour of this Renowned City, as well as you are Stewards and Governours of Publick Charitys, that you maintain theſe your Hoſpitable Feaſts, to encourage more ſuch Charitable Benefactions, by the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial of thoſe <hi>whoſe Names are as precious Oyntment;</hi> nor will I go about to ſtint the Allowance of your domeſtick friendly Meetings by the <hi>Fannian</hi> Law,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106986:13"/> which permitted the Citizens of <hi>Rome</hi> in the height and flouriſhing of their Empire, to ſpend no more at a Feaſt, and the <hi>Sempronian</hi> Law no more at a Marriage Feaſt, than would amount to a Crown of the Sun in the modern Coin; I will not preſume to contract your Entertainments by ſo ſtrict Laws as thoſe, any more than I would confine your Eſtates by that <hi>Agrarian</hi> Law which the Common-wealths-men (that wou'd gladly have a ſhare in your Lands) would fain intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce upon you; But tho' I do not preſcribe to your Liberality at the Table, <hi>hitherto ſhalt thou go and no further;</hi> for abundantly enough and to ſpare is allow'd to a Feaſt, as our Bleſſed Lord approv'd by his own Practice, when he Treated the Multitude, <hi>there were taken up of the Fragments twelve Baskets full:</hi> tho' I do not offer to ſet you ſuch bounds as you ſhall not paſs in your Civil Entercourſes, yet I muſt needs Add, there is danger enough when the <hi>Rich do but Feaſt</hi> one another, elſe it wou'd never have been given in Caution, <hi>When thou ſhalt have Eaten, and art full, then beware leſt thou forget the Lord;</hi> whom they are leaſt apt to remember, <hi>who lye upon Beds of Ivory, and ſtretch themſelves upon their Couches, and Eat the Lambs out of the Flock, and the Calves out of the midſt of the ſtall, that drink Wine in Bowls, but they are not grieved for the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction of</hi> Joſeph: there is hazard alſo of feeding the diſeaſe of our nature, too worldly Affections in Treating our Friends and Relations. The firſt great Feaſt we Read of was <hi>Gen.</hi> xxi. A better
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106986:13"/> Man than he that made it, or a juſter Occaſion of Feaſting could ſcarce have been found, <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of <hi>Iſaack</hi> and of all the Faithful, kept it in Token of Gratitude to God for the Son of his Old Age, and the Heir of Promiſe, yet it prov'd of Melancholy Conſequence; it ended in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Sorrow and <hi>Iſhmael</hi>'s Baniſhment. But if our Feaſts bear no reſemblance with the Ancient Feaſts of Charity, if there be no Conſideration had of the Empty Souls, while <hi>we have enough and to ſpare,</hi> if God were Angry with his Peoples Faſts in <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> for want of Alms joyn'd with them, then how much more will he be with our Feaſts, if we let our Brethren ſtarve while we are indulging our ſelves; But if to keep far enough from that uncharitable <hi>waſting Sin</hi> (as Divines call it) we aim at Charity in an Heroick Degree, Chriſt here chalks out the way to it, <hi>When thou makeſt a Feaſt, Call the Poor,</hi> that is make it ſometimes on purpoſe to Solace and Relieve them; wherein there is</p>
            <p>Firſt imply'd a Seaſonable Advice for thoſe who have not the Courage to give as long as they have the Power to keep any thing, but talk of Bequeath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much when it ſhall be no longer their own; they are Fools if they do not know what they Tempt thoſe whom they pinch, to wiſh and pray for, and they are the greater Fools if they deny the Poor and themſelves too, yet ſo do moſt of the Covetous, but he that Counſels us here <hi>to Feaſt the Poor,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends we ſhould do it before there is nothing leſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106986:14"/> us but <hi>to feaſt the Worms;</hi> I confeſs if men have a fixt and ſincere Intention of giving all in a lump to ſome very great and good Work for which they gather, God may be honour'd by ſuch a whole free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will Offering from them Living or Dying; but yet 'tis ſurer a great deal which is ſo given already as to be without power of a Revocation; 'tis ſafer to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute with your own hands, than to truſt in others what you could not obtain of your ſelves to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form; 'tis greater conſolation to ſee with your own Eyes ſo many of your good Works upon the ſile, and it is more efficacious than any thing to encreaſe your <hi>Charity,</hi> or even to inflame it, when the Head, the Hand, the Heart, is conſtantly exerciſed and yet <hi>never weary of well-doing;</hi> This is to keep up a Trade of <hi>Charity,</hi> where it may be truly ſaid, that <hi>the light Gains make the heavy Purſe,</hi> continual Acts of Mercy and ſpreading our Alms thin on many leſſer Objects of our Compaſſion: This is moſt properly <hi>Sowing,</hi> and <hi>ſowing plenteouſly,</hi> 'tis laying up a growing <hi>Treaſure in Heaven,</hi> 'tis <hi>gathering to ones ſelf a good Reward againſt the Day of Neceſſity,</hi> and think what a folly it is to leave the Torch be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind one, being to go through a dark and diſmal Paſſage, what madneſs to leave what thou loveſt ſo well in the place from whence thou art going, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of ſending it before to <hi>that abiding City.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, <hi>When thou makeſt a Feaſt, Call the Poor;</hi> it ſuppoſes a carefulneſs for them, a double-diligence firſt to find out and invite them, then to receive
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106986:14"/> and refreſh them; This is ſo extremely far from <hi>turning away thy face front any Poor Man,</hi> as rather to travel in queſt of ſuch pitiful Objects, this is what <hi>David</hi> calls, <hi>Conſidering the Poor and Needy,</hi> Laying out our Thoughts for them, and ſending out our Meſſengers, as did the Venerable Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and Charitable Old Man; <hi>When I ſaw abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Meat,</hi> ſaid <hi>Tobit, I ſaid to my Son, go and bring what Poor Man ſoever thou ſhalt find out of our Brethren, who is mindful of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, <hi>to Feaſt them</hi> means to Relieve them <hi>Plentifully,</hi> tho' it does not mean a <hi>Miſer</hi>'s Feaſt, for one Luxurious Meal, nor ſhould the Poor be Treated with meats compounded and metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos'd by the Rules of Irregular Gluttony: yet let it be <hi>a Feaſt,</hi> a frugal one but ſtill a Feaſt to them, enough to <hi>ſatisfie the Soul of the Hungry</hi> ſhould be ſometimes prepar'd on purpoſe for them, and thus has God provided for them, that ſome of the beſt and moſt delicious Meats are the very cheapeſt and eaſieſt to be had; ſince it was not only the Privilege of <hi>the Land of Promiſe,</hi> but a Common Bleſſing almoſt upon all Lands, <hi>to flow with Milk and Honey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, <hi>When thou makeſt a Feaſt, Call the Poor,</hi> and if this can hardly be done ſo ſilen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly, but that ſome little Notice will be taken of it, then be not Aſham'd of ſeeming to do that Good which really thou do'ſt; as this is a common Fault, now Piety is driven into Corners, and <hi>Charity</hi> it ſelf is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106986:15"/> become a puſillanimous, a bluſhing thing before the Men of a Giant-like mind, who <hi>make a mock of Sin</hi> and of Virtue too; nor be Afraid <hi>to let thy Light ſhine before Men,</hi> ſince all manner of <hi>Good-Works</hi> that happen <hi>to be ſeen of Men,</hi> are not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unpleaſing to God, but only ſuch as are done with ſo vile a principal End as to be ſeen of Men, and not with a primary Intent, that thoſe Men <hi>may Glorifie thy Father which is in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>When thou makeſt a Feaſt, Call the Poor,</hi> that is Call them to be thy welcome Gueſts, thy humble Friends, thy Spiritual Kindred; ſince Chriſt has Call'd them his <hi>Brethren,</hi> ſince he has made them <hi>Heirs</hi> and <hi>Coheirs</hi> with himſelf and thee; Lay aſide thy ſupercilious Demeanour toward them, nay put off now and then that Awful Diſtance which Decency requires thee to keep at other times; Let ſome of them at theſe good Times be ſeated at thy Table with thee; thy Betters have us'd them more familiarly, they <hi>have girded themſelves and ſerved them</hi> with a Real not an Affected Humility; The Greateſt Kings and Queens have not thought it too little for them <hi>to waſh and kiſs</hi> their Feet, in Imitation of him that introduc'd the ſame ſignificant Ceremony, propoſing it for a Pattern to his Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; and where can even Royal Duſt and Aſhes lay themſelves low enough in an Office of Devotion to <hi>him</hi> in the Proxies or in the Perſons of thoſe that are <hi>his,</hi> when <hi>he the Son of God, he who thought it no Robery to be Equal with God, yet took upon him
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106986:15"/> the form of a Servant,</hi> and was content to Abaſe himſelf, even <hi>to kiſs the Feet</hi> of the Traytor <hi>Jud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</hi> But tho we are not obliged to fall ſo low to the Poor as always to ſet them above us, yet there is one Complement eſſential to make it a Feaſt, <hi>in all thy Gifts ſhew a Chearful Countenance,</hi> ſays the Wiſe Man, <hi>for God loves a Chearful Giver,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle; and then there is felt and enjoy'd true pleaſure in the Act of Charity; when Chearfulneſs dilates and enlarges the Heart of the <hi>Alm'ner</hi> as well as the Soul of the <hi>Alms-Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now 'tis high time for me to interpoſe one Caution, and that Caution will naturally meet me upon my third Head of Diſcourſe: That fit Objects for the Charity of the Rich muſt be ſuch as are Poor indeed, for ſuch they are not, nor are they properly ſo called that are in condition to help them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they muſt be really helpleſs Creatures, <hi>the Maimed, the Lame, the Blind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For to nouriſh Idleneſs, the certain fore-runner, if not the Companion of Wickedneſs, is but miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Charity, and thoſe that have two hands left them to feed one Mouth, are to be counted with thoſe that are Rich enough, if they are no way diſabled; from ſuch our Alms would be more kindly withdrawn than extended to them; or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſtead of theſe <hi>External</hi> Works of Mercy, thoſe which the Schoolmen call <hi>Internal,</hi> ſhould be applyed to them; ſuch as Good Counſel, with Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance toward their Settlement, to make them
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106986:16"/> ſome way uſeful to their Country, or at leaſt no longer Burthens of the Earth; or if Advice be loſt upon them, another Office of Charity to their Souls at leaſt, even Caſtigation and Compulſion upon them is but their Due as well as our Duty to ſolicit it. I muſt have leave in this place to lament the miſerable Abuſe of ſo vaſt a <hi>Fund for Charity,</hi> as perhaps no Kingdom under Heaven can boaſt the like, I mean that Yearly Treaſure rais'd by virtue of that exceedingly well meant and ill manag'd Act for every Pariſh in the Nation to maintain their <hi>Poor,</hi> who thereupon make themſelves ſuch on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and are become perfect Oppreſſors in the Land, which they will not ſet their Hands to Cultivate, how low ſoever the Husband-man's Trade is grown for want of Labourers, that Honourable thriving Profeſſion heretofore, but now decayed and fallen together with your Rents; which is all for want of Executing with that wholſome Statute-Law, the ſame in ſubſtance with that Apoſtolical Canon, <hi>If any one would not Work neither ſhould he Eat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But on the other ſide I muſt needs highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and congratulate this City, ſo many Work-Houſes to Chaſtiſe and Reduce the Vagrant and Vicious Poor; ſo many Late uſeful Inventions to Employ the <hi>Willing-Poor,</hi> and to put even ſuch as are half <hi>Cripples</hi> in a way of getting their Bread; ſo many worthy Active Undertakers to find'em work, that they <hi>may Eat the Labour of their Hands,</hi> who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they are that Engage in <hi>this Labour of Love,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:106986:16"/> to <hi>Gather</hi> the <hi>Diſperſed</hi> from door to door, and to make 'em live by themſelves and their own handy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works, they do as it were treat them every day, and may <hi>the good Conſcience</hi> of their own deeds be to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a <hi>continual Feaſt!</hi> But the moſt goodly ſight of all in this noble City are ſo many fair Hoſpitals, either to i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cloſe thoſe whom the Hand of God has toucht with Lunacy; or to breed up poor Children abandon'd to the narrow mercy of the wide World; or to keep thoſe from ſtarving that are poor indeed, <hi>the Maim'd, the Lame, and the Blind:</hi> Let me but Read you a true Report, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I hope Strangers when they ſurvey theſe M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>numents of Antient and Modern Piety, will not ſay that the Church of <hi>England</hi> owns any ſuch <hi>Solifidian</hi> Doctrine, as tends to the Diſparagement of <hi>Good Works,</hi> none will imagine that our Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation is not a Soil for Charity to proſper upon, where has it grown or flouriſht more than it has among us both heretofore, and of late? I have been Askt abroad by way of Reflexion, Who Built our Churches in <hi>London?</hi> I have Anſwered, The Old ones were moſt of them built before the Corruptions of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſince the Fire of <hi>London</hi> we know who Rebuilt 'em. But no where does the <hi>City-Charity</hi> look more hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, nor promiſes greater Advantages to the <hi>Publick</hi> as well as to the <hi>Poor,</hi> than it does in thoſe ſeveral Royal and Ample Foundations lately Repair'd and Reſtor'd to receive thoſe wretched Infants, expos'd to a Condition well nigh as deplorable as that whom
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106986:17"/> the <hi>Prophet</hi> deſcribes; to theſe the King is inſted of God, and not only ſays unto them when <hi>they are as</hi> it were <hi>in their Bloud, Live;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut takes ſuch honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Care of their Education, that they may not live in vain; may God Almighty add to the King's Life thoſe Years which the King by his Bounty and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs has prevented from being cut off, from the Lives of theſe <hi>Little Ones;</hi> or from being ſo miſemploy'd as would in all likelihood have brought 'em to ſhameful Deaths.</p>
            <p>And may his Majeſty live to perfect his other moſt Royal, moſt Chriſtian Deſign in the Neighbourhood of this City, that ſtately Pile whoſe Walls are now happily riſing for the reception of <hi>Lame and Maimed Souldiers;</hi> that after <hi>Brave Men</hi> have ſerv'd the King in his juſt Wars, they may not want a proviſion and place of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirement in their Old broken Age, where they may end their Days in ſerving God, and ſtill praying for the Life of the King.</p>
            <p>Such as theſe be they Young or Aged, as long as they are uncapable of ſubſiſting by themſelves, our Saviour in the words of my Text, effectually recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends them to be treated with all Humanity and Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Mercy; ſuch Poor as theſe are the Wealth of a Chriſtian Corporation, as that holy Deacon S. <hi>Laurence</hi> Anſwered that Cruel and Covetous Preſident, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of him the Gold and Silver riſing from the great <hi>Oblations at the Altar</hi> where he Miniſtred, he muſter'd up a vaſt number of Poor Saints, ſome without Eyes, ſome whoſe Arms were quite wither'd away,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106986:17"/> others decrepit with Age, who had loſt the uſe of their Feet, and ranging all theſe miſerable creeping things ſo as the Governour migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have his full view of them, <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>theſe are the Churches hidden Treaſure:</hi> but I may ſay theſe are not only as the <hi>Publick Stock</hi> of your City, but as its Walls and Bulwarks: and the mercy ye ſhew to ſuch as theſe, is as one of the Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of your Power, like one of your <hi>Gold Chains,</hi> 'tis <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Compariſon and not mine, <hi>Let not Mercy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake thee, bind it about thy Neck.</hi> Prov. iii. 3. as if <hi>Solomon</hi> himſelf for outward Glory had <hi>never been arrayed like one of thoſe,</hi> who ſhine within and without by their noble Acts of mercy.</p>
            <p>And thus I am coming into my fourth and laſt part, the Glories of this Grace or the great Reward of Charity, ſo much the greater when it comes the longer it is a coming; <hi>And thou ſhalt be bleſſed for they cannot recompenſe thee;</hi> they whom thou chooſeſt to Relieve in thy diſ-intereſted Charity can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not if they would repay thee, but he that Aſſuredly can, Infallibly will; ſo this is placing our Charity as Uſurers do their Mony, moſt willingly on good Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to thoſe that will keep it longeſt, ſo they ſhall be certainly paid <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe upon <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> for it, and conſider'd for the very forbearance of their Intereſt: Not that the Charitable Man goes without a Bleſſing in this Life; the Poor have a ſpecial Prerogative from God <hi>to Bleſs;</hi> and as Rich as <hi>Job</hi> was before his Adverſity, he was highly pleas'd to receive their Benedictions; <hi>When the Ear heard me then it bleſſed me, becauſe I delivered the Poor that Cryed, and the Fatherleſs, and him that had none
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106986:18"/> to help him, the Bleſſing of him that was ready to periſh came upon me;</hi> And well may their Bleſſings be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, when on the other ſide their Curſes are ſo formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable; for ſure the Son of <hi>Syrach</hi> knew what he ſaid, <hi>Turn not away thine Eye from the Needy, and give him none Occaſion to Curſe thee; for if he Curſe thee in the bitterneſs of his Soul, his Prayer ſhall be heard of him that made him:</hi> Strange that an Imprecation ſhould be called a Prayer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch a <hi>Prayer as is turn'd into Sin</hi> upon him that puts it up, and yet is received by God as a Petition or Charge upon him that provokes and extorts it; But on the other ſide, how many are the Bleſſings that are even heapt upon <hi>the Liberal Soul that deviſeth Liberal things, and by Liberal things ſhall he be eſtabliſht;</hi> If <hi>Bleſſing</hi> him in his Perſon that <hi>conſiders the Poor and Needy, If delivering him in the time of trouble,</hi> If <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving him and keeping him Alive that he may be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon Earth, if Comforting him when he lyeth ſick upon his Bed</hi> and <hi>making all his Bed in his ſickneſs,</hi> if theſe are mighty Bleſſings, all theſe are put together in one place, and a Concordance would help me to a thouſand more ſuch places, full of Bleſſings as great and as certain as theſe, and all theſe on this ſide Heaven: But the ſtrongeſt motive of all is that in my Text, the moſt unreſiſtible Argument for giving Alms, tho 'Hoping for nothing again in this world, is <hi>That thou ſhalt be Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſt at the Reſurrection of the Juſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not ſaid thou ſhalt merit Heaven by thy Good-Works, the beſt, the nobleſt Act of Charity muſt needs be that, <hi>to lay down our Lives for our Brethren;</hi> yet
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106986:18"/> Martyrdome it ſelf ought not to be put into the Scale, as if it were Weighty or <hi>Worthy</hi> enough to deſerve <hi>an exceeding and eternal weight of Glory;</hi> for <hi>I reckon</hi> (ſays St. <hi>Paul) that the ſufferings of this preſent time are not worthy to be Compared with the Glory that ſhall be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in us,</hi> yet, ſays the ſame Apoſtle in an other place, <hi>our light Affliction which is but for a moment, worketh for us a far more exceeding and eternal weight of Glory;</hi> ſo our Doing Good as well as our ſuffering Evil are a ſure means to <hi>Obtain</hi> though not to <hi>Merit,</hi> and as the certain Recompenſe in the World to come is here made a moſt forcible Argument for Charity, ſo the Charity that ſome Exerciſe without receiving their Recompence in this World, is an invincible Proof of a World to come.</p>
            <p>For now ſuppoſe a man with all this heap of pitiful Accidents upon him which our Saviour puts together in the Text, <hi>Poor, Maimed, Lame,</hi> and <hi>Blind,</hi> add to theſe the Torments of Cramps and Stone, to keep him perpetually on the wrack from his Child-hood to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream Old-Age; and yet this poor man perſeveres in the Fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, and practiſes more Charity even that of Alms, than do all the Rich, parting with <hi>his two Mite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (as the Widdow did <hi>with all her Living)</hi> when he hears of one in more immediate danger of ſtarving than himſelf; he will truſt to him that feeds the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, to ſupply his next days Exigence; tho <hi>his patient Continuance in well-doing</hi> may qualifie and enable him to cry out, <hi>Centuplum in hac Vita,</hi> that God has <hi>given him a hundred fold in this Life,</hi> of Joy in the Holy-Ghoſt,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106986:19"/> and Expectations of Bliſs, yet it can never conſiſt with the Goodneſs of God to ſuffer any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly good Man feeding himſelf with ſuch Expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to be at length defrauded and diſappointed; and the Juſtice of God requires that he be one day recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſt, <hi>ſeeing it is a Righteous thing with God,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>to recompenſe Tribulation to them that trouble his Saints, And to thoſe who are troubled reſt with us, when the Lord Jeſus ſhall be revealed from Heaven with his mighty Angels:</hi> And ſeeing it is a Stoical or rather a Chimical, an Empirical Divinity, that by making Virtue its own Reward, prepares a great Diſſolvent to Annihilate Virtue it ſelf, and bring it to nothing, then ſince that God is Juſt and moſt perfect Juſtice it ſelf, there needs muſt be a <hi>Day of Recompenſe, a Time of Refreſhing,</hi> a time when every <hi>Lazarus that received his Evil things ſhall be Comforted,</hi> and when every Rich Man that has already <hi>Received</hi> and Abus'd <hi>his Good things ſhall be Tormented;</hi> But this Time and that Recompenſe cannot be to a Man in ſuch a Caſe as I have ſuppos'd, till after this Life, therefore it proves ſufficiently that there is <hi>a Life to Come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if ſuch a practice of <hi>Good Works</hi> in the midſt of ſuch almoſt inſupportable Evils of this Life, be a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſtrong enough to prove there's a Life to come, <hi>ſo that a Man ſhall ſay verily there is a Reward for the Righteous;</hi> then ſuch a Life and ſuch a Reward once prov'd, is the ſtrongeſt Argument in the World, and the moſt perſuaſive to the Practice of ſuch <hi>Good-Works:</hi> only to mention this Argument of a <hi>Recompenſe at the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106986:19"/> Reſurrection,</hi> were <hi>Charity</hi> never ſo cold, were ſufficient to raiſe it up from the dead again; to think that many a poor Good Man, whom you have ſeen frozen almoſt to Death this laſt hard Winter, and have ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed him with the means to warm him till <hi>his loyns bleſt you,</hi> many a <hi>Blind, Maimed</hi> or <hi>Lame,</hi> whom you have as it were led by the hand out of his preſent miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſhall one day become a Guide to you as you were to him formerly; that he ſhall have the Agility of a Spirit, and the diſcerning power of a <hi>Spirit of a Juſt Man made perfect,</hi> to behold you coming toward the place of Bliſs, and to call you as the good Angel did the Apoſtle, <hi>Come up hither;</hi> if this will not prevail with you <hi>to Call the Poor,</hi> and give them a little Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in this World, nothing will ever move you: this is that Powerful Motive our Saviour uſes, to <hi>make our Selves friends</hi> in Heaven, by giving Alms upon Earth, <hi>that when we fail they may receive us,</hi> that the <hi>Heirs of Salvation</hi> may be allowed and ſent forth by God to meet us when we enter into the <hi>New World,</hi> that they may Conduct us <hi>into their Everlaſting Habitations;</hi> for as St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> Argues upon that place, <hi>If we go to a ſtrange City we need a Guide, much more to another World, when the Soul is torn away from the Body, the ſtaff upon which it lean'd, then it has Dreads and Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror</hi> (ſay he) <hi>when it quits this Fleſh.</hi> And if you will forgive me the laying of one Quotation upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſpeaks ſo pathetically to the ſame Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <note place="margin">De Morta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> how they ſhall welcome us into the <hi>Other World,</hi> for whom we had Charity or Kindneſs in this, that with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106986:20"/> a Lively Deſcription and Diſcourſe of His, ſince I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not with a better, I ſhall Conclude mine. <hi>Who is there</hi> (ſay he) <hi>who being to ſayl homeward to his Friends does not make wiſhes for a proſperous Gale, that he may quickly embrace thoſe whom he loves ſo dearly? Let us account that</hi> Paradice <hi>is our Country, as we have look'd upon the</hi> Patriarchs <hi>to be our</hi> Parents; <hi>why do we not haſten and move forward apace to ſee that</hi> Country <hi>of ours, and ſalute thoſe</hi> Parents? <hi>there are a vaſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Perſons very dear unto us that expect us, our Forefathers, our Brethren, our Children, a numerous Company that long for our coming to them, being ſecure of their own, and ſtill ſolicitous for our Imortality: to ſee them again and grow into Embraces with them, How will it Affect and Tranſport both us and them? what kind of Bleſs is there in thoſe Heavenly Kingdoms, which conſiſts with no fear of Dying, with an Aſſurance of</hi> Living Eternally? <hi>there is the Apoſtles glorious Quire, there the Prophets honourable Senate, there the Legions of Crowned Martyrs that Dyed and Suffer'd Valiantly, there the Triumphant Virgins that have ſubdued and tamed by the mighty hand of Continence the</hi> Carnal De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of the Body, <hi>there the merciful Men who have dealt their Doles and Largeſſes to the Poor and Needy; Let us haſten away to theſe, wing'd with a fervent deſire to be with theſe, to be with Chriſt. Let this be the Aim of all our wiſhes, Let God ſee ſuch thoughts in us, Let Chriſt ſee the Travail of our Souls, the Intent of our Faith, who will aſſuredly give them larger Rewards, whoſe Souls are more enlarged toward Heaven and Eternity.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Now unto the King Eternal, Immortal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:106986:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
